Guide to the Jesse Brundage Sears Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Jesse Brundage Sears papers
1860-1973
SC0005
Sears, Jesse Brundage, 1876-1973
13.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Jesse Brundage Sears and Robert Sears, 1965, 1974, 1978, and 1979.
Information about Access
Professor Sears' papers were originally received in two lots prior to January of 1965. These groups were combined to form SC 5 when the old Stanford Collection became the holdings base of the University Archives in that year. The portion of the following register which covers the first six boxes was done at that time.
Subsequently, following Professor Sears' death in December of 1973, his son, Professor Emeritus Robert Sears, donated another group of the senior Dr. Sears' professional and biographical material. This group expanded the chronological range of the collection and furnished a good deal more manuscriptal material than had been included in the orginal gift. This later donation is described in the following register as boxes 7-11.
In June of 1979, Robert Sears donated yet another group of his father's records to the Archives. For the most part this material consists of correspondence between family members and friends, and covers the years 1860-1973. There is a small amount of material relating to Sears' professional life, mostly correspondence with Ellwood Cubberley. Several account books, pocket diaries or memo books, information on Sears' family history and genealogy, and copies of pages (not bound) from his wife, Stella's autobiography, make up the remainder of this addition to the collection. A preliminary guide to these later boxes (12-14) is contained in the register following box 11.
Information about Access
None.
Biographical Note
Dr. Sears was a Professor of Education at Stanford University from 1912-1942. He was born in 1876 and died in 1973.
Scope and Contents note
DESCRIPTION OF COLLECTION
The Sears Collection represents the combination of two groups of papers obtained prior to January 1965 with another large assemblage of papers added in March of 1974. A third addition was added to this collection in July of 1979. Both the pre-1965 and 1974 papers include four categories of data. A relatively small collection of Sears' correspondence in his professional capacities is present in both sets. Some personal history appears in Box 2 (part of the pre-1965 material), and a larger amount in Box 7 (part of the 1974 material). Except for the last three boxes which were added in 1979 and contain mostly family and personal correspondence, the bulk of the collection consists of Sears' writings, which are divided into a manuscript category and a reprint category. It should be noted that these four categories are intermixed in the pre-1965 material (first six boxes), and separated in the 1974 material. The material added in 1979 also includes account books, memo or pocket diaries, information on the Sears family history and some professional correspondence with Ellwood Cubberley.
MAJOR CORRESPONDENTS
Most of the correspondence in this collection is in the most recent (1979) addition of material. As yet these boxes have received only preliminary attention, and the list of major correspondents is not complete. Among them are Ellwood Cubberley, J.B. Sears' wife Stella Richardson Sears, his children: Jean, Robert and Norman Sears, his brothers and sisters, C.B. Sears, C.N. Sears, G.W. Sears, B.L. Sears H.J. Sears C.G. Sears, and D.L. Sears, as well as numerous other relatives and friends.
Collection Contents
- SCHOOL SURVEY CORRESPONDENCE, 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- SPEAKING ENGAGEMENTS CORRESPONDENCE, 1927-8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- SUMMER SCHOOL LECTURES, CORRESPONDENCE, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- ST. LOUIS MEETING OF A. E. R. A., 1935-6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- CORRESPONDENCE WITH McGRAW-HILL, 1937, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  (SEE ALSO MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE)
- CUBBERLEY BOOKS, REVIEWS AND CORRESPONDENCE, 1955-60 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- CUBBERLEY H. S. CORRESPONDENCE, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE, 1922-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- CUBBERLEY RELATED PAPERS (Box 1, Folder 9)
- CLASS OUTLINES (Box 1, Folder 10)
- LECTURE NOTES (Box 1, Folder 11)
- FELLOWSHIP FORUM OF PALO ALTO (Box 1, Folder 12)
- MSS. OF PUBLISHED ARTICLES (SAMPLES OF WORKS) (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
- MISCELLANEOUS MSS. OF WRITINGS (POSSIBLY DRAFT OF TAMALPAIS SURVEY) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- UNFINISHED MANUSCRIPT OF BOOKS ON ADMINISTRATION (Box 2, Folder 4)
- MISC. MSS. OF WRITINGS-SOME DRAFTS (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
- UNFINISHED MSS. OF BOOKS PUBLIC SCHOOL FINANCE (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 1930 WHITE HOUSE CONFERENCE ON CHILD HEALTH AND PROTECT (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 1932 CALIFORNIA WHITE HOUSE CONFERENCE ON CHILD HEALTH AND PROTECTION (Box 2, Folder 7)
- CLIPPINGS (Box 2, Folder 8)
- BIOGRAPHICAL ITEMS (Box 2, Folder 9)
- REVIEWS BY J. B. S. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- PUBLIC ADDRESSES (Box 2, Folder 11)
- SCHOOL SURVEYS. PRINTED REPORTS, IF ISSUED ARE FILED WITH THE RELATED PAPERS IN THE FOLLOWING CARTONS. (Box 3)
- OAKLAND SPELLING INVESTIGATION, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- SALINAS UNION HIGH SCHOOL., 1918 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- PRESTON SCHOOL OF INDUSTRY, WATERMAN, CALIFORNIA, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- BOISE [IDAHO] CITY SCHOOLS - MISSING 5/96, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- ARLINGTON [MINNESOTA] SURVEY, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- PHOENIX UNION HIGH SCHOOL, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
- MARYSVILLE [CALIFORNIA] UNION HIGH SCHOOL, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- BERKELEY SCHOOL PROPERTIES SURVEY, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- BERKELEY SCHOOL BUSINESS MANAGEMENT SURVEY, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- ANTIOCH HIGH SCHOOL, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- NAPA SCHOOL SURVEY, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- TAMALPAIS SURVEY, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- FALL RIVER JOINT UNION H. S. CONSOLIDATION, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- SUTTER COUNTY INSTRUCTIONAL SURVEY, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- SACRAMENTO SCHOOL SURVEY, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- SANGER SCHOOL BUILDING SURVEY, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- PITTSBURG [CALIFORNIA] SURVEY, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- ALBANY [CALIFORNIA] SURVEY, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- SACRAMENTO SCHOOL SURVEY REVIEW, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- PALO ALTO ADDRESS ON POSSIBLE SERVICE OF SURVEYS TO PALO ALTO, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- MARYSVILLE ELEMENTARY SCHOOL, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- SANGER ELEMENTARY SCHOOL, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- MODESTO JUNIOR COLLEGE, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- TRACY UNION HIGH SCHOOL, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- STOCKTON SCHOOL SURVEY, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- ADMINISTRATIVE ORGANIZATION OF SACRAMENTO'S SCHOOL SYSTEM, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- ADMINISTRATIVE SURVEY OF PLACER UNION HIGH SCHOOL AND PLACER JUNIOR COLLEGE, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- WASCO [CALIFORNIA] SURVEY, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- SAN FRANCISCO CURRICULUM, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- ALASKA SCHOOL, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- STANFORD SCHOOL OF EDUCATION, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- SURVEY BIBLIOGRAPHIES (Box 5, Folder 11)
- BOUND VOLUME OF REPRINTS. MISCELLANEOUS REPRINTS AND BOOKS WRITTEN BY J. B. S. (Box 6)
- Personal History and Professional Correspondence.
  The following folder register covers that portion of the Sears Collection donated by Professor Robert Sears in 1974. This portion is divided according to the type of material (as described in the short register) and covers the last four boxes of the collection.
  - Personal History: Autobiographies of Jesse Brundage Sears ( The Story of My Life and Work, and his wife Stella R. Sears ( My Story, 1959 1948 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Personal History: Sears Family Biographies: Charles B., George W., and Edith F. Sears. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Personal History: Sears Family Biographies: Harry Johnson Sears. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Personal History: Sears Family Genealogical Data. Genealogical Chart (Rolled) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Personal History: Personal Correspondence, 1909-1966 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Personal History: Personal Financial Data, The 1928 material consists of stock purchase orders and receipts, company statements. The 1960's material consists of tax records and dividend statements., 1928 and 1960-1965 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Personal History: Personal Financial Data, The material of this folder consists of tax records and dividend statements., 1967 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Personal History: Personal Financial Data, The material of this folder consists of tax records and dividend statements., 1968 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Personal History: Professional Memorabilia, General. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Personal History: Professional Memorabilia, Newspaper Clippings. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Personal History: Professional Memorabilia, Scratch Notes and Notebooks. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Professional Correspondence: General, A - M. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    (The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, chronologically thereafter when a correspondent is represented by more than one item.)
  - Professional Correspondence: General, N - Z. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    [Note: Folders 12 and 13 feature correspondence from Ellwood P. Cubberley, David Starr Jordan, Kidder Institute, Edward Krehbiel, Ray Lyman Wilbur, the Universities of California, Minnesota, Missouri, Penn, Pitt, Utah and Wisconsin, and the various publishers of Dr. Sears' books.]
  - Professional Correspondence: Letters relating to Sears Scholarship awards at Kidder Institute in Missouri. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Professional Correspondence: Letters of greeting upon Dr. Sears' retirement from active teaching in 1942 [bound in leather notebook]. (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Manuscriptal Materials.
  - Major Mss: Classroom Organization and Control, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Typewritten manuscript of first ten chapters.
  - Major Mss: Classroom Organization and Control, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Typewritten manuscript of latter ten chapters.
  - Major Mss: The School Survey, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Typewritten manuscript of Part I (pp. 1-186).
  - Major Mss: The School Survey, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Typewritten manuscript of remaining Parts (pp. 187-424).
  - Major Mss: The Sacramento School Survey, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Typewritten manuscript of work done with Almack, Proctor, and Eelts, (pp. 1-270).
  - Major Mss: The Sacramento School Survey, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Typewritten manuscript of work done with Almack, Proctor, and Eelts, (pp. 271-506).
  - Major Mss: The Sacramento School Survey, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Typewritten manuscript (pp. 507-757) plus appendix and handwritten notes.
  - Major Mss: Modesto Junior College Survey, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Handwritten manuscript.
  - Major Mss: City School Administrative Controls, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Typewritten manuscript of first draft material, including notes and some handwritten pages.
  - Major Mss: City School Administrative Controls, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Typewritten manuscript of first draft material.
  - Major Mss: City School Administrative Controls, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Typewritten manuscript of first four chapters.
  - Major Mss: City School Administrative Controls, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Typewritten manuscript of latter four chapters.
  - Major Mss: Public School Administration, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Typewritten manuscript of seven chapters (pp. 1-189).
  - Major Mss: Public School Administration, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Typewritten manuscript of Chapters 8 through 13, (pp. 190-407).
  - Major Mss: Public School Administration, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Typewritten manuscript of final chapters (pp. 408-488) plus handwritten draft of early chapters.
  - Major Mss: Nature of the Administrative Process, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Major Mss: Nature of the Administrative Process, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Typewritten manuscript of Chapters 5 through 9.
  - Major Mss: Nature of the Administrative Process, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Typewritten manuscript of Chapters 10 through 14.
  - Major Mss: Nature of the Administrative Process, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Typewritten manuscript of annotated bibliography and index; also handwritten manuscript of index.
  - Major Mss: Nature of the Administrative Process, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Typewritten manuscript of various scattered pages and complete set of plate proofs for final version.
  - Major Mss: Cubberley of Stanford: and His Contribution to American Education, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Handwritten manuscript of Preface through Chapter 5, with typewritten comments and changes by Adin D. [UNK] Sears' collaborator.
  - Major Mss: Cubberley of Stanford..., 1957 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Handwritten manuscript of Chapters 6 through 8 with Henderson's typewritten comments and changes.
  - Major Mss: Cubberley of Stanford..., 1957 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Handwritten manuscript of Chapters 9 through 11 with Henderson's typewritten comments and changes.
  - Major Mss: Cubberley of Stanford..., 1957 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Handwritten manuscript of Chapter 12 through Appendices and Index with Henderson's comments and changes.
  - Major Mss: My Life and Work, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Complete typewritten manuscript.
  - Major Mss: My Life and Work, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    Complete typewritten draft with handwritten notes and corrections.
  - Major Mss: My Life and Work, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    Complete handwritten draft.
  - Major Mss: Sears' portion of an untitled, apparently unpublished cooperative book (written with Cubberley and Almack). Chapters 17-22., 1940 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Major Mss: Sears' portion of an untitled, apparently unpublished cooperative book (written with Cubberley and Almack). Chapters 23-32., 1940 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Minor Mss: Articles and Other Writings, 1921-22 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Minor Mss: Articles and Other Writings, 1924-29 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Minor Mss: Articles and Other Writings, 1930-34 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Minor Mss: Articles and Other Writings, 1935-37 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Minor Mss: Articles and Other Writings, 1941-49 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Minor Mss: Articles and Other Writings, 1950-53 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Minor Mss: Articles and Other Writings, Publication and, Date Uncertain (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Minor Mss: Articles and Other Writings, Publication and, Date Uncertain (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Minor Mss: Articles on Rural Education, Publication and, Date Uncertain (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Minor Mss: Addresses and Speeches, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Minor Mss: Studies and Surveys, Publication and, Date Uncertain (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Minor Mss: Book Reviews, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Minor Mss: Sears' Own Student Memorabilia [papers, class outlines and summaries], 1910-11 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Minor Mss: Miscellany [notes and outlines for articles or speeches, student paper by Myrtle G. Welton], Dates Uncertain (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Publications and Reprints. (Box 11)
  [Box 11, a large record carton, contains journals and magazines which include articles or reviews by J.B. Sears. The box also contains copies of some of these same articles and reviews in reprint form.]
- 1979 Addenda
  This addenda to SC 005 (boxes 12-14) contains material given to the Archives by Robert R. Sears (son of J.B. Sears) in 1979. The bulk of the material is personal correspondence to and from family members and close friends, although there is a small amount of professional correspondence with Ellwood Cubberley. In addition the boxes contain several account books, pocket diaries, copies of J.B. Sears' wife's autobiography and copies of the Sears genealogy. The correspondence covers the years 1860-1973.
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1860-1973 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence by individual, 1860-1973 (Box 12)
  - Sears family history and genealogy (Box 12)
  - Misc. essays and poetry of J.B. Sears (Box 12)
  - Misc. essays and stories of Stella Richardson Sears (Box 12)
  - Memo books, pocket diaries (Box 12)
  - Memoirs of J.B. Sears' trip to Europe, undated (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, still in envelopes (Box 13)
  - Unbound copies of Stella Richardson Sears' autobiography (Box 13)
  - Account books (8), 1936-1962 (Box 14)
  - Folder of correspondence, etc. relating to J.B. Sears' death in 1973 (Box 14)
- PUBLIC SCHOOL ADMINISTRATION. Typed and handwritten manuscript, fifteen chapters, undated
  - Preface and Introduction (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 1: An Approach to the Study of School Administration (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 2: The Tools of Research and Library Usage (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 3: The Background of Social Administration (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 4: Professional Organizations, Serial Publications, and Public Documents of the Field (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 5: Our Theory of Public School Administration (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 6: Federal Government and Education (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Chapter 7: State School Administration (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Chapter 8: County and Rural School Administration (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Chapter 9: Financing Public Education (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Chapter 10: Local School Administration (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Chapter 11: Personal Management (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Chapter 12: Supervision and Research (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Chapter 13: School Business Management (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Chapter 14: School Buildings (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Chapter 15: The Administration of a School (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Bibliographic Index Cards (Box 15, Folder 17)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-1990-112
  - Education and the War Emergency: Letters and Bulletins from California School Executives Covering Emergency Activities assembled vol. 1, locations A-O, [1941-1942], 1942 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Education and the War Emergency: Letters and Bulletins from California School Executives Covering Emergency Activities assembled vol. 2, locations P-Z, [1941-1942], 1942 (Box 16, Folder 2)
Material Removed from the Collection
Multiple copies of the Sears genealogy and duplicates of forms. Three glass negatives of Sears' grandparents have been put in the photograph collection.